<body>
<section level="1" id="section1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="para2"> Many infections only occur as isolated cases, short chains of transmission, or as small infection clusters&lpar;i. e. intertwinedtransmission chainsnull. Examples include zoonotic infections with relatively weak human&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmission as well as vaccine&hyphen;preventable infections in settings of high vaccination coverage&nbsp; <citref rids="ref1 ref2 ref3 ref4 ref5 ref6 ref7">1&ndash;7</citref>. Even though transmission is limited, these diseases are an important public health concern. For example, zoonotic infections can adapt for increased human&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmission and then cause greater or even pandemic spread&nbsp; <citref rids="ref8 ref9 ref10">8&ndash;10</citref>. In addition, decreased voluntary vaccination, difficulty with vaccine delivery or changes in vaccine efficacy can allow growth of the number of individuals susceptible to preventable diseases and thus cause larger outbreaks&nbsp; <citref rids="ref3 ref11">3,11</citref>. Self&hyphen;limited&lpar;or {\emsubcritical}<emph type="italic">subcritical</emph>nulltransmission also characterizes diseases that are on the brink of elimination such as smallpox during its worldwide eradication campaign or polio today&nbsp; <citref rids="ref12 ref13 ref14">12&ndash;14</citref>. </p><p id="para3">Despite a need to monitor disease burden, manage the risk of disease emergence or enhance disease elimination, the surveillance and control of subcritical infections can be challenging. Resource&hyphen;poor countries, which are home to many zoonoses, have many logistical hurdles that impact the quality of surveillance and control interventions. Meanwhile, even in developed countries, reactive control strategies such as isolation protocols for vaccine&hyphen;preventable diseases have significant sociological impact beyond the immediate financial costs. Because of these challenges, the overarching goal is to optimize control interventions for the least amount of effort and expense. It is therefore important to gain as much quantitative information about disease transmission as possible from existing surveillance data. This includes monitoring how transmission varies with time, location and other epidemiological characteristics of individual cases. By improving the understanding of mechanisms of disease transmission, finer tuning within the spectrum of intervention strategies becomes possible&nbsp; <citref rids="ref15 ref16">15,16</citref>. Such mechanistic understanding can guide the response to a diverse range of threats that include emerging infections&lpar;e. g. , Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirusnull, vaccine&hyphen;preventable infections&lpar;e. g. , measlesnulland antibiotic resistance&nbsp; <citref rids="ref17 ref18">17,18</citref>. </p><p id="para4">For ethical and logistical reasons, population&hyphen;level studies of infectious disease transmission in humans typically involve retrospective statistical analysis rather than controlled prospective experimentation. Given this constraint, one approach for evaluating mechanisms underlying transmission patterns is to compare the transmissibility of two distinct, but related populations. In this manuscript, we demonstrate how the strength and heterogeneity of transmission can be compared for two different populations or types of infection sources. We then show how our framework provides insight into the transmission patterns of a variety of subcritical diseases. This analysis builds upon earlier studies that were limited to estimating transmission parameters from chain size distributions and addressing issues of surveillance bias&nbsp; <citref rids="ref19 ref20">19,20</citref>. </p><p id="para5">Mathematically, the transmissibility of a group of infected individuals can be quantified by determining the group&rsquo;s effective reproduction number, null. This number represents the mean number of secondary cases caused by an infected case. However, because of the stochastic nature of disease transmission, the realized numbers of secondary infections caused by a given infected individual will vary. nullis a more general parameter than the oft cited<emph type="italic">basic</emph>reproduction number<equ id="equ8" type="inline">
<tex>
$R_0$

</tex></equ>
, which more specifically represents the mean number of secondary cases caused by the first infected case in a completely susceptible population&nbsp; <citref rids="ref21">21</citref>. Whennulll, transmission cannot reach epidemic proportions, whereas if<equ id="equ9" type="inline">
<tex>
$R_\mathrm{eff}>1$

</tex></equ>
there is a potential for epidemic spread. Thus, our focus on subcritical diseases implies that, overall, nullwill be less than one and transmission will be characterized by self&hyphen;limited clusters of infection. However, our method still permits the possibility that cases can be divided into two groups in which one group has anulll, and the other group has a<equ id="equ10" type="inline">
<tex>
$R_\mathrm{eff}>1$

</tex></equ>
. </p><p id="para6">Our study builds upon the prior success of inferringnullfrom the size distribution of observed transmission chains&nbsp; <citref rids="ref1 ref2 ref22">1,2,22</citref>. The same distributions can also be used to infer the degree of transmission heterogeneity, represented by the dispersion parameter, <equ id="equ11" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
&nbsp; <citref rids="ref19 ref20 ref23">19,20,23</citref>. A high degree of heterogeneity represents a scenario where some individuals are predisposed to spreading infection to a larger number of people&lpar;i. e. , nullsuperspreaders&rsquo;null. When models of chain size distributions incorporate bothnulland<equ id="equ12" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
, excellent agreement can often be found between observed data and model predictions&nbsp; <citref rids="ref19 ref20 ref23">19,20,23</citref>. </p><p id="para7">Our goal is to evaluate specific hypotheses regarding disease transmission by testing whethernulland<equ id="equ13" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
differ between two groups of cases. Our analyses differ from more traditional epidemiological approaches based on case&hyphen;control studies&lpar;and many other study designsnullin that we focus on transmissibility instead of individual&hyphen;level risk factors for disease susceptibility. We demonstrate our methodology by considering four subcritical infections&lpar;MERS&hyphen;CoV, measles, monkeypox and smallpoxnulland three types of data&lpar;size distribution of infection clusters, transmission chain data and infection source classificationnullto answer four different questions based on published data. For MERS&hyphen;CoV, we use chain size distributions to determine whether an apparent decrease innullduring the latter half of 2013  was statistically significant. Assessing temporal trends ofnullhas important implications for evaluating the risk of endemic MERS&hyphen;CoV transmission and the impact of control interventions. For measles, we use chain size distributions to compare two locations&lpar;United States and Canadanulland test whether there is a significant difference innull, which would suggest important differences in vaccine distribution, social connectedness, and&sol;or demographics. For smallpox and monkeypox, we use case series resolved by infection generation to determine whether there are significant differences between the first and subsequent generations of spread&nbsp; <citref rids="ref24 ref25">24,25</citref>. This analysis allows us to assess whether variation in the number of contacts or the timing of control interventions can be linked to changes innull. It also allows us to test the validity of a specificnullrandom network&rsquo;model that relates the contact patterns of primary and secondary cases. We then test whether there is a significant difference between inferred transmission parameters for animal&hyphen;to&hyphen;human and human&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmission of monkeypox, which provides insight into the mechanisms of zoonotic spillover. Our analysis of chain size distributions also provides perspective on the surveillance required to detect a change innull, such as the expected increase in human monkeypox transmission following the eradication of smallpox. Each of the scenarios considered represents a unique example of how quantitative characterization of transmissibility can provide insight into the effectiveness of control interventions and risk assessment for future spread. </p></section>
<section level="1" id="section2"><title>Methods</title>
<section level="2" id="section3"><title> Modeling framework</title><p id="para8"> The stochastic nature of infectious disease transmission is particularly important whennulll, as it can result in substantial variation in the size distribution of transmission chains. In this case it is helpful to model transmission as a branching process&nbsp; <citref rids="ref26">26</citref>. In this formulation, the offspring distribution specifies the probability that an infected individual will cause<equ id="equ14" type="inline">
<tex>
$0,1,2,\ldots$

</tex></equ>
new infections. We specify the corresponding offspring probabilities to be<equ id="equ15" type="inline">
<tex>
$q_0,q_1,q_2,\ldots$

</tex></equ>
, with<equ id="equ16" type="inline">
<tex>
$\sum_{j=0}^{\infty}q_j=1$

</tex></equ>
. To facilitate likelihood calculations&lpar;as seen belownull, the offspring distribution can be represented as a generating function, <equ id="equ17" type="inline">
<tex>
$Q(s)=\sum_{j=0}^{\infty}q_j\cdots^j$

</tex></equ>
, in which the polynomial coefficients are the offspring probabilities&nbsp; <citref rids="ref26 ref27 ref28">26&ndash;28</citref>. </p><p id="para9">In line with research demonstrating how the strength and variability of transmission can be modeled&nbsp; <citref rids="ref23">23</citref>, we assume the<equ id="equ18" type="inline">
<tex>
$q_i$

</tex></equ>
&rsquo;s follow a negative binomial offspring distribution with a mean ofnulland a dispersion parameter of<equ id="equ19" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
. The dispersion parameter represents the degree of transmission heterogeneity, with lower values of<equ id="equ20" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
corresponding to higher variance. The S methods&lpar;Text S1nullexplains how our simple model of disease transmission can be used to calculate the likelihood for various types of observed data. These likelihood calculations permit inference of the strength and variability of transmission for individual cases, in terms ofnulland<equ id="equ21" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
. All calculations were conducted with either Matlab or R. Code for all analyses is available at&colon;<?up?><?show +"linkList"tpmkset "web2","description","","*ttps://github.com/sbfnk/nbbpchainsize",0,0,2$10#?><?show $60#?tbklnk=="web2"$62#?><url url="ttps://github.com/sbfnk/nbbpchainsize">https&colon;&sol;&sol;github. com&sol;sbfnk&sol;nbbpchainsizes</url><?tbklnk?><?down?>". </p></section>
<section level="2" id="section4"><title>Determining model parsimony when comparing two sets of data</title><p id="para10"> By calculating the likelihood of an observed set of transmission events, we can probe whether there is statistical support for differences in transmission between two pre&hyphen;specified populations, <equ id="equ22" type="inline">
<tex>
$A$

</tex></equ>
and<equ id="equ23" type="inline">
<tex>
$B$

</tex></equ>
. In our general model, the two types of individuals have distinct negative binomial characterizations and thus there are four parameters in total. We label these four parameters<equ id="equ24" type="inline">
<tex>
$R_A$

</tex></equ>
, <equ id="equ25" type="inline">
<tex>
$R_B$

</tex></equ>
, <equ id="equ26" type="inline">
<tex>
$k_A$

</tex></equ>
and<equ id="equ27" type="inline">
<tex>
$k_B$

</tex></equ>
with the subscripts corresponding to the type of individual. Five simpler models that are nested within the 4 &hyphen;parameter model can be constructed by assuming<equ id="equ28" type="inline">
<tex>
$R_A=R_B$

</tex></equ>
, <equ id="equ29" type="inline">
<tex>
$k_A=k_B$

</tex></equ>
and&sol;or<equ id="equ30" type="inline">
<tex>
$k_A=k_B=1$

</tex></equ>
&lpar;Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig1">Figure&#146;1</figref>null. The specific test case of<equ id="equ31" type="inline">
<tex>
$k=1$

</tex></equ>
is chosen for the nested models because this corresponds to a geometric offspring distribution which is the expectation for a traditional SIR or SEIR model. These models assume homogenous mixing with constant infectivity over an exponentially distributed infectious period&nbsp; <citref rids="ref29">29</citref>. For each model, we determine the parameter values&lpar;MLEnullthat maximize the log&hyphen;likelihood. The 95 &percnt;confidence intervals and confidence regions shown in the figures were found by profiling on<equ id="equ32" type="inline">
<tex>
$R_A$

</tex></equ>
and&sol;or<equ id="equ33" type="inline">
<tex>
$R_B$

</tex></equ>
and employing the likelihood ratio test&nbsp; <citref rids="ref30">30</citref>. Model comparison is accomplished via the Akaike Information criterion&lpar;AICnull&nbsp; <citref rids="ref31">31</citref>. </p><fig id="fig1" num="1" type="figure"><caption><emph type="bold">Six ways of modeling the transmission of two populations whose transmissibility is being comparedThe dashed lines distinguish the models according the assumptions that are made about whethernulland the dispersion parameter are the same or different for the two populations.</emph><?FIGTITLE 1?> The axis on the right indicates the number of parameters used in each model.<?FIGTITLE 0?> This is the sum of the number of parameters used to modelnull&lpar;either 1  or 2 nulland the number of parameters used to model dispersion&lpar;either 0 , 1  or 2 null.<?FIGTITLE 0?> </caption><caption type="doi">10.1371&sol;journal ppat 1004452.g001</caption><graphic id="journal.ppat.1004452.g001.tif"></graphic></fig><p id="para11">To identify whether there is statistical support for a difference innullfor two data sets, the AIC scores were computed for all six aforementioned models. A difference innullwas deemed statistically significant according to the rule that the model with the best AIC score cannot be within two AIC units of a model that supports identical values ofnullfor the two sets of simulations. This rule is in approximate alignment with the commonly used likelihood ratio test for establishing statistical support for the use of an extra parameter with 95 &percnt;confidence, but we could not employ the likelihood ratio test explicitly because some pairs of models we consider are not nested. We verified the internal consistency of our modeling framework by applying this method to simulated data&lpar;S material, Text S1null. </p><p id="para12">We used parametric bootstrapping to evaluate the type I error and the power for detecting a change innullfor our analyses. Specifically, for every analysis we simulated 20 , 000  new data sets. Each simulated data set replicated the two populations involved in the analyses&lpar;e. g. MERS&hyphen;CoV chains before and after June 1 , 2013 null. Two models were simulated. Half of the simulations used two distinct values ofnulland<equ id="equ34" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
that matched the inferred values of our unrestricted four&hyphen;parameter model. The other half of the simulations used a single value ofnulland<equ id="equ35" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
that matched the inferred values of our two&hyphen;parameter model, which requires both<equ id="equ36" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
andnullto be the same for all cases seen in the observed data. Our inferential algorithm for ascertaining a statistically significant difference in the inferred value ofnullwas then applied to all simulations. The type I error of an analysis&lpar;i. e. theprobability that the analysis would falsely claim thatnullis different for the two types of cases considerednullwas estimated as the proportion of simulations based on the two&hyphen;parameter model that were found to have a statistically significant difference innullfor the two types of cases. The parametric bootstrap probability&lpar;or powernullof detecting a change innullwas estimated as the proportion of simulations based on the four&hyphen;parameter model that were found to have significant difference innullfor the two types of cases. </p></section></section>
<section level="1" id="section5"><title>Results</title><p id="para13"> Data used to generate all results can be found in the supplemental material&lpar;Text S2null. </p>
<section level="2" id="section6"><title>The apparent trend towards decreased human&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmission of MERS&hyphen;CoV during the second half of 2013  may be a reflection of stochasticity rather than a true decrease innull</title><p id="para14">Since 2011 , there have been over 500  confirmed cases of MERS&hyphen;CoV, and over 140  associated deaths, suggesting a case fatality rate of 28 &percnt;&nbsp; <citref rids="ref32">32</citref>. The persistent occurrence of small outbreaks is due to zoonotic spillover&nbsp; <citref rids="ref33 ref34 ref35">33&ndash;35</citref>. MERS&hyphen;CoV may be a new virus, as the most recent common ancestor of viral samples from infected patients was estimated to have occurred after September 2010 &nbsp; <citref rids="ref34">34</citref>. The novelty of this virus and its high case fatality rate underscore the significance of monitoring the transmission of MERS&hyphen;CoV. Although human&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmission has been relatively limited so far, withnulllikely less than one, there is concern that future adaptation that could lead to spread similar to sudden acute respiratory syndrome&lpar;SARSnullin 2003 . Health authorities have prudently instituted a variety of infection control policies and procedures and a trend towards decreasingnullhas been reported&nbsp; <citref rids="ref34">34</citref>. Since verification of the effectiveness of control has important implications, we reconsidered the evidence for a trend towards decreasingnull. </p><p id="para15">To avoid artifacts of assembling multiple data sources, we restricted our analysis to the previously reported chain size distribution for all MERS&hyphen;CoV cases in the Arabian Peninsula occurring before August 8 , 2013 &nbsp; <citref rids="ref34">34</citref>. Previous analysis of these data shows thatnullis 0.74&lpar;95 &percnt;CI 0.53&ndash;1.03nullbefore June 1 , 2013  and 0.32&lpar;95 &percnt;CI 0.14&ndash;0.65nullafter June 1 , 2013 . Our results replicate the finding that independent evaluation of cases before and after June 1 , 2013  results in an estimate of 0.7 and 0.3 fornullrespectively&lpar;Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig2">Figure&#146;2</figref>and Table&nbsp;<tblref rids="tbl1">Table&#146;1</tblref>null. When our six models are compared, we do not find statistical support for models with different valuesofnullbefore and after June 1 , 2013 . This is again consistent with the results of prior studies that determined a p&hyphen;value of 0.07 for change innull, but our analysis allows the possibility of a high degree of transmission heterogeneity. </p><fig id="fig2" num="2" type="figure"><caption><emph type="bold">Assessing temporal variation of MERS&hyphen;CoV transmission in the Arabian Peninsula before Aug 8 , 2013 AnullThe results of estimating the effective reproduction number, null, for six inter&hyphen;related models of transmission are shown.</emph><?FIGTITLE 1?> The contours show the 95 &percnt;confidence regions for three models that allow different values ofnullfor cases occurring before versus after June 1 , 2013 .<?FIGTITLE 0?> The distinction is that each model makes different assumptions about the degree of transmission heterogeneity&lpar;as explained in the textnull.<?FIGTITLE 0?> The black dot shows the maximum likelihood estimation&lpar;MLEnullestimate of thenullvalues for these three models.<?FIGTITLE 0?> The dashed grey line indicates whennulldoes not change with time.<?FIGTITLE 0?> The dashed colored lines show the MLE estimate and 95 &percnt;confidence interval ofnullfor the three models that assume transmissibility of cases is independent of time.<?FIGTITLE 0?> The slight displacement of the colored lines from the dashed grey line is only for visual clarity.<?FIGTITLE 0?> BnullThe fit of our preferred model to the early MERS&hyphen;CoV chain size data is shown&lpar;Table&nbsp;null.<?FIGTITLE 0?> The error bars of the data correspond to 95 &percnt;confidence intervals as determined by non&hyphen;parametric bootstrapping of chain sizes.<?FIGTITLE 0?> CnullThe fit of our preferred model to the late MERS&hyphen;CoV chain size data is shown.<?FIGTITLE 0?> </caption><caption type="doi">10.1371&sol;journal ppat 1004452.g002</caption><graphic id="journal.ppat.1004452.g002.tif"></graphic></fig><tbl id="tbl1" num="1"><tbl:title><emph type="bold">Table 1.</emph></tbl:title><emph type="bold">Inference results for assessing temporal variation of MERS&hyphen;CoV transmission in the Arabian Peninsula before Aug 8 , 2013 </emph>Maximum likelihood parameters, log&hyphen;likelihood scores and AIC values are shown for the various inference methods described in the text. <equ id="equ26" type="inline"><tex>$Early$</tex></equ>and<equ id="equ27" type="inline"><tex>$late$</tex></equ>corresponds to transmission before and after June 1 , 2013 , respectively. The left column identifies the method by indicating the parameter constraints used. The model with<equ id="equ28" type="inline"><tex>$k_\mathrm{early}=k_\mathrm{late}=1$</tex></equ>is chosen as the reference point for the<equ id="equ29" type="inline"><tex>$\DeltaAIC$</tex></equ>calculations since it has the best overall AIC score. Although this model has the best<equ id="equ30" type="inline"><tex>$AIC$</tex></equ>score, it assumes two different values ofnull. Erring on the side of requiring 95 &percnt;confidence to distinguishnullvalues, our method does not indicate that there is enough statistical support for using two different values ofnullbecause the<equ id="equ31" type="inline"><tex>$\DeltaAIC$</tex></equ>score of the<equ id="equ32" type="inline"><tex>$R_\mathrm{early}=R_\mathrm{late}$</tex></equ>model is less than two. Thus the<equ id="equ33" type="inline"><tex>$R_\mathrm{early}=R_\mathrm{late}$</tex></equ>is our preferred model&lpar;indicated by the bold cellnull. There were a total of 81  early cases among 21  chains and a total of 28  late cases among 19  chains. </tbl></section>
<section level="2" id="section7"><title>nullis significantly different between transmission of measles in the United States&lpar;1997 &ndash;1999 nulland Canada&lpar;1998 &ndash;2001 null</title><p id="para16">Local elimination of measles is dependent on vaccination programs, and the potential for re&hyphen;emergence necessitates continued surveillance and re&hyphen;assessment of vaccination strategy&nbsp; <citref rids="ref1 ref3 ref36 ref37 ref38">1,3,36&ndash;38</citref>. Even where elimination has been achieved, there can be sporadic clusters of infection due to a combination of geographic importation and pockets of susceptibility&nbsp; <citref rids="ref39 ref40 ref41">39&ndash;41</citref>. Geographical differences in transmission may arise due to differences in cultural practices, public health guidelines, population density and other factors. Methods that delineate whether differences innullare statistically significant for two different regions can therefore help to identify key differences in transmission potential and thus pinpoint opportunities for improved control. </p><p id="para17">Measles data in the United States&lpar;1997 &ndash;1999 nulland Canada&lpar;1998 &ndash;2001 nullare reported according to the size of infection clusters&nbsp; <citref rids="ref39 ref40">39,40</citref>. Most infection clusters have a single primary infection, but even when multiple primary infections exist&lpar;as in the case of a cluster with six cases in the United Statesnull, the likelihood calculation needed for assessing differences innullis straightforward&lpar;S Material, Text S1null. When the two data sets are compared, the results indicate thatnullfor the United States and Canada are significantly different&lpar;Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig3">Figure&#146;3</figref>and Table&nbsp;<tblref rids="tbl2">Table&#146;2</tblref>null. Meanwhile, the results also confirm previous studies that infer a high degree of transmission heterogeneity in measles transmission&nbsp; <citref rids="ref19 ref23">19,23</citref>. This can be seen from Table&nbsp;<tblref rids="tbl2">Table&#146;2</tblref>since the MLE estimates for<equ id="equ37" type="inline">
<tex>
$k_\mathrm{USA}$

</tex></equ>
and<equ id="equ38" type="inline">
<tex>
$k_\mathrm{Canada}$

</tex></equ>
are less than one and the<equ id="equ39" type="inline">
<tex>
$\DeltaAIC$

</tex></equ>
value of the model with<equ id="equ40" type="inline">
<tex>
$k_\mathrm{USA}=k_\mathrm{Canada}=1$

</tex></equ>
is large. On the other hand, there is negligible statistical support for distinct values of<equ id="equ41" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
in the two countries. The type I error for this situation was estimated to be 4.9&percnt;by parametric bootstrapping. </p><fig id="fig3" num="3" type="figure"><caption><emph type="bold">Comparing the transmissibility of measles in the United States&lpar;1997 &ndash;1999 nulland Canada&lpar;1998 &ndash;2001 nullThe layout is analogous to Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig2">Figure&#146;2</figref>, except that the axes represent locations rather than time periods.</emph><?FIGTITLE 1?> Because of the ambiguity in the correct classification of an infection cluster with six cases that had two primary infections, this data point was not included in panels B and C&lpar;but it was included in the calculations for panel A, as our method accounts for all possible chains in this clusternull.<?FIGTITLE 0?> </caption><caption type="doi">10.1371&sol;journal ppat 1004452.g003</caption><graphic id="journal.ppat.1004452.g003.tif"></graphic></fig><tbl id="tbl2" num="2"><tbl:title><emph type="bold">Table 2.</emph></tbl:title><emph type="bold">Inference results for comparing the transmissibility of measles in the United States&lpar;1997 &ndash;1999 nulland Canada&lpar;1998 &ndash;2001 null</emph>The layout is analogous to Table&nbsp;<tblref rids="tbl1">Table&#146;1</tblref>. Although thenullNone&rsquo;model, has a<equ id="equ46" type="inline"><tex>$\DeltaAIC$</tex></equ>within two&lpar;i. e. ourchosen threshold for statistical significancenullof the best model, our analysis still suggests thatnullis statistically different for the United States and Canada, because both of these models have distinctnullvalues for the two countries. Thus the<equ id="equ47" type="inline"><tex>$k_\mathrm{USA}=k_\mathrm{Canada}$</tex></equ>model&lpar;bold cellnullis our preferred model. There were a total of 336  cases in the United States among 166  chains and a total of 274  cases in Canada among 49  chains. </tbl></section>
<section level="2" id="section8"><title>Significant differences existed between primary and secondary transmission of smallpox in Europe,  1958 &ndash;1973 </title><p id="para18"> Smallpox is the only human disease to have been eradicated and thus represents a tremendously successful use of control&nbsp; <citref rids="ref12">12</citref>. During the endgame of smallpox eradication in the middle of the 20  th century, smallpox cases in Europe resulted in rapid implementation of quarantine and control procedures. Transmission data for smallpox infections in Europe that occurred during this period provide an opportunity to investigate how control interventions impacted the transmissibility of primary cases caused by geographic importation relative to secondary cases resulting from local transmission&nbsp; <citref rids="ref12">12</citref>. </p><p id="para19">Smallpox clusters were tabulated according to the number of cases in each generation of spread&nbsp; <citref rids="ref12">12</citref>. The inference results indicate that secondary cases transmitted significantly less than primary cases&lpar;seen by the lack of overlap of contours with the grey line in Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig4">Figure&#146;4</figref>and by the statistical selection of the non&hyphen;restricted model in Table&nbsp;<tblref rids="tbl3">Table&#146;3</tblref>null. In fact, the effectiveness of control procedures can be quantified by looking at the ratio of reproduction numbers for primary and secondary transmission&lpar;Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig4">Figure&#146;4</figref>insetnull. The ratio of the maximum likelihood values for<equ id="equ42" type="inline">
<tex>
$R_\mathrm{seconday}$

</tex></equ>
to<equ id="equ43" type="inline">
<tex>
$R_\mathrm{primary}$

</tex></equ>
suggests that control reducednullby 75 &percnt;. Meanwhile, for both primary and secondary transmission, a high degree of transmission heterogeneity is evident&lpar;since the MLE estimates of<equ id="equ44" type="inline">
<tex>
$k_\mathrm{primary}$

</tex></equ>
and<equ id="equ45" type="inline">
<tex>
$k_\mathrm{seconday}$

</tex></equ>
are substantially less than one and the<equ id="equ46" type="inline">
<tex>
$\DeltaAIC$

</tex></equ>
value of the<equ id="equ47" type="inline">
<tex>
$k_\mathrm{USA}=k_\mathrm{Canada}=1$

</tex></equ>
model is largenull. Based on selection of the unrestricted model, and the associated estimates of<equ id="equ48" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
, there appears to be significantly more heterogeneity of disease transmission for secondary cases than for primary cases. The type I error for this analysis was estimated to be 5.1&percnt;by parametric bootstrapping. </p><fig id="fig4" num="4" type="figure"><caption><emph type="bold">Comparing the transmissibility of primary and secondary cases for smallpox in Europe, 1958 &ndash;1973 The layout is analogous to Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig2">Figure&#146;2</figref>except the axes distinguish between transmission of primary and secondary cases.</emph><?FIGTITLE 1?> The inset of panel A replicates the results when<equ id="equ1" type="inline"><tex>$k_\mathrm{primary}$</tex></equ>and<equ id="equ2" type="inline"><tex>$k_\mathrm{seconday}$</tex></equ>are inferred separately&lpar;our preferred modelnull, except that the y&hyphen;axis is now the ratio of<equ id="equ3" type="inline"><tex>$R_\mathrm{seconday}$</tex></equ>to<equ id="equ4" type="inline"><tex>$R_\mathrm{primary}$</tex></equ>.<?FIGTITLE 0?> For panels B and C, the data is shown only for cases where there was a clear record of subsequent secondary infections&lpar;as opposed to knowing that four cases lead to ten secondary cases in aggregatenull.<?FIGTITLE 0?> The 95 &percnt;confidence intervals were found by parametric bootstrap on this more limited data set.<?FIGTITLE 0?> </caption><caption type="doi">10.1371&sol;journal ppat 1004452.g004</caption><graphic id="journal.ppat.1004452.g004.tif"></graphic></fig><tbl id="tbl3" num="3"><tbl:title><emph type="bold">Table 3.</emph></tbl:title><emph type="bold">Inference results for comparing the transmissibility of primary and secondary cases for smallpox in Europe, 1958 &ndash;1973 </emph>The layout is analogous to Table&nbsp;<tblref rids="tbl1">Table&#146;1</tblref>. There were a total of 36  primary cases and 537  secondary cases. </tbl></section>
<section level="2" id="section9"><title>Differences between primary and secondary transmission of human monkeypox in the Democratic Republic of Congo&lpar;1981 &ndash;1984 nullappears negligible</title><p id="para20"> Following the eradication of smallpox in 1979 , the World Health Organization was concerned that subsequent cessation of smallpox vaccination would allow other diseases to flourish&nbsp; <citref rids="ref42">42</citref>. Monkeypox was of particular concern because exposure to smallpox or smallpox vaccination provided protection against monkeypox. Estimates ofnull, extrapolated from contact tracing data gathered during rigorous surveillance in the Democratic Republic of Congo&lpar;formerly Zairenullduring 1981 &ndash;1984 , provided re&hyphen;assurance that endemic transmission would not be sustainable even when population immunity to monkeypox waned&nbsp; <citref rids="ref43">43</citref>. </p><p id="para21">The initial analysis of monkeypox transmission did not quantitatively compare the transmission of primary cases&lpar;i. e. thosecaused by animal&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmissionnullto the transmission of secondary cases&lpar;i. e. thosecaused by human&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmissionnull. Since the characteristics of these cases differ&lpar;i. e. onlyprimary cases required exposure to infected animalsnull, differences in transmission are possible. Increased transmission of secondary cases could also arise from population structure&nbsp; <citref rids="ref25">25</citref>, or evolutionary adaptation&nbsp; <citref rids="ref8 ref10">8,10</citref>. For example, network models have proposed that social structure impacts the effective reproduction number of individual cases&nbsp; <citref rids="ref44 ref45 ref46 ref47 ref48">44&ndash;48</citref>. In particular, the random network model that we have considered&lpar;S material, Text S1nullpredicts that secondary cases transmit more than primary cases since highly&hyphen;connected individuals are most likely to both acquire and spread infection. If this aspect of the random network model is accurate, the risk of endemic spread as population immunity wanes may be higher than previously expected. This is becausenullfor secondary transmission would be expected to increase more thannullfor primary transmission. It is thus important to ascertain whether there is a difference between primary and secondary transmission that is consistent with the random network hypothesis. </p><p id="para22">As part of the monkeypox surveillance efforts, transmission was tabulated according to the number of cases in each generation of spread&nbsp; <citref rids="ref43 ref49">43,49</citref>. These data can be used to ascertain whether there is a statistically significant difference in primary versus secondary transmission&lpar;Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig5">Figure&#146;5</figref>and Table&nbsp;<tblref rids="tbl4">Table&#146;4</tblref>null. The results indicate a lack of evidence for a difference between thenullof primary and secondary cases&lpar;seen by noting the overlap of contours with the grey line in Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig5">Figure&#146;5</figref>and because the preferred model in Table&nbsp;<tblref rids="tbl4">Table&#146;4</tblref>has<equ id="equ49" type="inline">
<tex>
$R_\mathrm{primary}=R_\mathrm{secondary}$

</tex></equ>
null. The low values for the maximum likelihood estimates of<equ id="equ50" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
are consistent with previous studies that infer a high degree of transmission heterogeneity in monkeypox transmission&nbsp; <citref rids="ref20 ref23">20,23</citref>. </p><fig id="fig5" num="5" type="figure"><caption><emph type="bold">Comparing the transmissibility of primary and secondary cases for human monkeypox in the Democratic Republic of Congo, 1981 &ndash;1984 The layout is analogous to Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig4">Figure&#146;4</figref>, except that the random network model has been added.</emph><?FIGTITLE 1?> The dotted line in panel A shows the relationship betweennullfor primary and secondary infections in the random network model profiled on<equ id="equ5" type="inline"><tex>$k_\mathrm{primary}$</tex></equ>.<?FIGTITLE 0?> The red curve shows the 95 &percnt;confidence interval for inference with the random network model.<?FIGTITLE 0?> The data shown in panels B and C are limited to instances where the transmission links could be unambiguously counted.<?FIGTITLE 0?> </caption><caption type="doi">10.1371&sol;journal ppat 1004452.g005</caption><graphic id="journal.ppat.1004452.g005.tif"></graphic></fig><tbl id="tbl4" num="4"><tbl:title><emph type="bold">Table 4.</emph></tbl:title><emph type="bold">Inference results for comparing the transmissibility of primary and secondary cases for human monkeypox in the Democratic Republic of Congo, 1981 &ndash;1984 </emph>The layout is analogous to Table&nbsp;<tblref rids="tbl1">Table&#146;1</tblref>, except that the random network model is added. There were a total of 147  primary cases and 62  secondary cases. </tbl></section>
<section level="2" id="section10"><title>The strength of animal&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmission of monkeypox appears to be similar to human&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmission</title><p id="para23"> Animal&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmission of monkeypox is an important contributor to overall disease burden. Determining the factors that allow continual introduction of monkeypox into human populations requires knowledge of how monkeypox maintains itself in reservoir hosts and the mechanisms that allow its transmission to humans&nbsp; <citref rids="ref6 ref50">6,50</citref>. In this section we assess whether an infected animal in contact with humans has a distinct set of inferred transmission parameters than infected humans. The relationship between infection source and transmissibility is an active area of research for many multi&hyphen;host diseases systems&nbsp; <citref rids="ref51 ref52 ref53 ref54 ref55">51&ndash;55</citref>, particularly for zoonotic infections. </p><p id="para24">Since the infection cluster data for monkeypox contains information on how many primary infections are in each cluster, it can be used to infer the amount of animal&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmission that occurs when infected animals make contact with humans. To accomplish this, we assume that the negative binomial offspring distribution that has been shown to be a good description of human&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmission&nbsp; <citref rids="ref23">23</citref>is also an effective model of animal&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmission. We let<equ id="equ51" type="inline">
<tex>
$R_{\mathrm{a}\to\mathrm{h}}$

</tex></equ>
represent the average number of primary cases caused by an infected animal that has contact with humans. Our results indicate that thenullfor human&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmission is similar to<equ id="equ52" type="inline">
<tex>
$R_{\mathrm{a}\to\mathrm{h}}$

</tex></equ>
&lpar;Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig6">Figure&#146;6</figref>and Table&nbsp;<tblref rids="tbl5">Table&#146;5</tblref>null. There is also evidence that animal&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmission is relatively homogeneous&lpar;since the<equ id="equ53" type="inline">
<tex>
$k_{\mathrm{a}\to\mathrm{h}}>1$

</tex></equ>
for the preferred modelnull. If one takes the MLEs of<equ id="equ54" type="inline">
<tex>
$R_{\mathrm{a}\to\mathrm{h}}$

</tex></equ>
and<equ id="equ55" type="inline">
<tex>
$k_{\mathrm{a}\to\mathrm{h}}$

</tex></equ>
for the preferred model at face value, then we estimate that at least one infection occurs 25 &percnt;of the time that a infected animal has contact with humans. </p><fig id="fig6" num="6" type="figure"><caption><emph type="bold">Comparing animal&hyphen;to&hyphen;human and human&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmissibility for human monkeypox in the Democratic Republic of Congo, 1981 &ndash;1984 The layout is analogous to Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig5">Figure&#146;5</figref>, but now the axes distinguish between animal and human transmission of monkeypox.</emph><?FIGTITLE 1?> The data shown in panel C is limited to instances where the transmission links could be unambiguously counted.<?FIGTITLE 0?> </caption><caption type="doi">10.1371&sol;journal ppat 1004452.g006</caption><graphic id="journal.ppat.1004452.g006.tif"></graphic></fig><tbl id="tbl5" num="5"><tbl:title><emph type="bold">Table 5.</emph></tbl:title><emph type="bold">Inference results for comparing animal&hyphen;to&hyphen;human and human&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmissibility for human monkeypox in the Democratic Republic of Congo, 1981 &ndash;1984 . </emph>The layout is analogous to Table&nbsp;<tblref rids="tbl1">Table&#146;1</tblref>. The<equ id="equ81" type="inline"><tex>$R_{\mathrm{a}\to\mathrm{h}}=R_\mathrm{eff}$</tex></equ>model was the preferred model since is within two of the model with the best<equ id="equ82" type="inline"><tex>$\DeltaAIC$</tex></equ>value, indicating there is not sufficient statistical support for distinct reproduction numbers. There were a total of 125  animal exposures leading to at least one primary case and 209  human cases. Despite the size of the data set, the<equ id="equ83" type="inline"><tex>$\DeltaAIC$</tex></equ>values are all quite small because there are large confidence intervals associated with the use of a truncated negative binomial distribution for inference <citref rids="ref19">19</citref>. </tbl></section>
<section level="2" id="section11"><title>Quantifying the surveillance needs for detecting a difference innullfor monkeypox since the eradication of smallpox</title><p id="para25"> Recently, a 20 &hyphen;fold increase in the incidence of monkeypox has been reported in the Democratic Republic of Congo&nbsp; <citref rids="ref56">56</citref>, and there is concern thatnullfor monkeypox may have increased. The lack of cross&hyphen;protective immunity to monkeypox from either smallpox vaccination or natural exposure to smallpox provides a mechanism for whynullwould increase&nbsp; <citref rids="ref57">57</citref>. However, land&hyphen;use changes that impact the potential for animal&hyphen;human transmission have also been suggested as a cause of an increase in monkeypox incidence&nbsp; <citref rids="ref58 ref59">58,59</citref>, and could do so without changingnull. There are no active interventions in place for monkeypox, so it is important to determine ifnullhas changed in order to understand the source of increased incidence. </p><p id="para26">Due to logistical barriers and the rare nature of the disease, acquiring data on monkeypox is a challenge&nbsp; <citref rids="ref42 ref56">42,56</citref>. In the wake of smallpox eradication, the infrastructure for monkeypox surveillance in 1980 &ndash;1984  was strong and well funded&nbsp; <citref rids="ref42">42</citref>. The detailed transmission data from this surveillance effort provide an estimate of 0.30 fornull&lpar;95 &percnt;CI&colon;0.21&ndash;0.42nulland 0.33 for<equ id="equ56" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
&lpar;95 &percnt;CI&colon;0.17&hyphen;0.75null <citref rids="ref20">20</citref>. For the 2005 &ndash;2007  surveillance effort, specific data on cluster sizes and individual&hyphen;level transmission are unavailable, so an assessment ofnullcannot be made. However, we can quantify the amount of data that would be needed in order to detect a change innullrelative to 1980 &ndash;1984 &nbsp; <citref rids="ref42 ref43 ref49">42,43,49</citref>. Simulations show that 200  clusters would provide 70 &percnt;power to detect an increase innullfrom 0.3 to 0.5&lpar;Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig7">Figure&#146;7</figref>Anull. As the number of observations increase, smaller changes are more readily noticeable. </p><fig id="fig7" num="7" type="figure"><caption><emph type="bold">Power to detect a change innullfor human monkeypox following smallpox eradicationAnullNumber of observed chains of transmission for monkeypox needed to detect a change innullrelative to 1980 &ndash;1984 .</emph><?FIGTITLE 1?> The 1980 &ndash;1984  monkeypox data&lpar;<equ id="equ6" type="inline"><tex>$R_\mathrm{eff}=0.3$</tex></equ>, <equ id="equ7" type="inline"><tex>$k=0.3$</tex></equ>nullare compared against a set of simulations with<equ id="equ8" type="inline"><tex>$k=0.33$</tex></equ>and<equ id="equ9" type="inline"><tex>$R_\mathrm{eff}=0.3+\DeltaR$</tex></equ>, with<equ id="equ10" type="inline"><tex>$\DeltaR$</tex></equ>specified on the x&hyphen;axis.<?FIGTITLE 0?> This procedure was repeated 1000  times for each value of the number of simulated chains, <equ id="equ11" type="inline"><tex>$N_c$</tex></equ>&lpar;as specified by the y&hyphen;axisnull.<?FIGTITLE 0?> For each value of<equ id="equ12" type="inline"><tex>$\DeltaR$</tex></equ>, the blue lines indicate the lowest number of observations for which a given power&lpar;as a proportion of the 1000  simulationsnullwas achieved.<?FIGTITLE 0?> The shades of blue&lpar;see legendnullindicate different levels of power for which this was done.<?FIGTITLE 0?> The straight red line corresponds to the mean number of chains that would have been observed for the 760  case detected during the 2005 &ndash;2007  monkeypox surveillanceprotect <citref rids="ref56">56</citref>for different values of<equ id="equ13" type="inline"><tex>$\DeltaR$</tex></equ>.<?FIGTITLE 0?> This line corresponds to<equ id="equ14" type="inline"><tex>$N_c=760*(1-R_\mathrm{eff})$</tex></equ>chains&lpar;since the average chain size is<equ id="equ15" type="inline"><tex>$\frac{1}{1-R_\mathrm{eff}}$</tex></equ>protect <citref rids="ref20">20</citref>null.<?FIGTITLE 0?> BnullThe power of the 2005 &ndash;2007  monkeypox surveillance data to detect a change innullfor monkeypox.<?FIGTITLE 0?> The black dots are the results of simulations, the blue line is a smooth fit to these.<?FIGTITLE 0?> This panel corresponds to a cross&hyphen;section of the figure in panel A along the red line.<?FIGTITLE 0?> </caption><caption type="doi">10.1371&sol;journal ppat 1004452.g007</caption><graphic id="journal.ppat.1004452.g007.tif"></graphic></fig><p id="para27">Consideration of the relationship betweennull, the number of chains and the number of cases provides perspective on the power of the recent surveillance efforts&lpar;2005 &ndash;2007 nullto detect a change innull&nbsp; <citref rids="ref56">56</citref>. It appears that there is 95 &percnt;power to detect an increase innullfrom 0.3 to 0.55 with analysis of the 760  observed cases&lpar;Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig7">Figure&#146;7</figref>Bnull. </p></section></section>
<section level="1" id="section12"><title>Discussion</title><p id="para28"> In summary, we have introduced and validated a method for comparing case data grouped into different categories and applied this method to a number of different scenarios. The versatility of the method has been explored through examination of a variety of diseases and data types. By providing quantitative information on transmission, surveillance needs, or the effectiveness of control interventions, each type of analysis has the potential to assist in epidemiological assessments and public health planning. </p>
<section level="2" id="section13"><title>MERS&hyphen;CoV transmission</title><p id="para29"> To reduce the burden of MERS&hyphen;CoV and reduce the risk of global spread, effective control procedures are of obvious importance. Given the large amount of resources and effort that have already been directed towards the control of MERS&hyphen;CoV, it would be reassuring to see a statistically significant decrease innull. When analyzing data on MERS&hyphen;CoV cases that presented before Aug 8 , 2013 , the unrestricted model had the best<equ id="equ57" type="inline">
<tex>
$AIC$

</tex></equ>
score. This unrestricted model suggested that becausenulldecreased from 0.7 to 0.3, control is over 50 &percnt;effective. However, there is not enough data to show statistical significance for this result. Meanwhile, our analysis is likely biased by the large outbreak that initiated the observational period for the data, so further studies are needed to more accurately evaluate the impact of control interventions&nbsp; <citref rids="ref60">60</citref>. </p><p id="para30">Unfortunately, the number of recent confirmed MERS&hyphen;CoV cases remains significant and the overall incidence may be increasing <citref rids="ref32">32</citref>. An increase in the number of cases can be caused by an increasednull, an increased rate of primary cases, or a combination of these effects&nbsp; <citref rids="ref61">61</citref>. Based on our observation thatnullis more likely to be decreasing after June 2013  than increasing, the paradigm of emergence that is most consistent with the previously published data we have analyzed is that MERS&hyphen;CoV incidence may be increasing in its non&hyphen;human reservoir, but that human&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmission remains stable. In fact, sequence data support the possibility of an expanding epidemic in animal hosts of MERS&hyphen;CoV that could lead to an increased incidence of primary cases&nbsp; <citref rids="ref34">34</citref>. However, other factors, such as seasonal drivers of transmission could also impact the temporal trend ofnull. An increased case load could also be observed if transmission patterns have not changed much, but greater interest in and knowledge of MERS&hyphen;CoV has led to improved surveillance. This could paradoxically lead to both an increase in the number of observed cases and a decrease in the observed value ofnullbecause of a greater chance of seeing a larger proportion of smaller outbreaks&nbsp; <citref rids="ref19 ref62">19,62</citref>. </p><p id="para31">Given the relative paucity of cases and uncertainties regarding case observation probability, it would be inappropriate to make a definitive statement concerning the cause of the apparent increase in MERS&hyphen;CoV incidence at this time. However, as more data on MERS&hyphen;CoV are reported, the types of analyses presented in this manuscript can be rapidly applied to address hypothesis&hyphen;driven questions concerning the temporal trends of incidence and the impact of control intervention. In particular there may be concerns that certain subgroups of MERS&hyphen;CoV cases may have increased transmission, such as those occurring in health care settings where nosocomial transmission is higher or in geographic regions where control interventions are harder to implement. Alternatively, as we have shown with smallpox, there may be a difference in the transmissibility of primary cases versus secondary cases. With more data, our method can help to quantify differences in transmission, and evaluate whether certain population subgroups may have annullthat exceeds the critical value of one. While it is not necessary for future data to be resolved to the level of individual transmission events, the types of analyses we have presented do require knowledge of chain size distributions rather than aggregate epidemic curve data. Meanwhile, an important gap in the currently available data is a quantitative assessment of the case reporting probability for MERS&hyphen;CoV cases and whether this is increasing with time. Improved knowledge of the reporting probability would permit adjustments to the likelihood calculations and reduce the bias of imperfect case ascertainment <citref rids="ref19">19</citref>. </p></section>
<section level="2" id="section14"><title>Measles transmission</title><p id="para32"> Our comparison of measles transmission in the United States and Canada provides a framework for elucidating geographic differences in transmission&lpar;Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig3">Figure&#146;3</figref>null. Interestingly, while our analysis supported a difference innullbetween the two countries, a difference in the degree of transmission heterogeneity&lpar;as quantified by the dispersion parameternullwas not identified. This apparent disassociation between the strength of transmissibility and the mechanisms of transmission heterogeneity may occur if the heterogeneity is due to intrinsic biological processes such as variability in viral shedding. However, the relationship between the value of dispersion parameter and various mechanisms of transmission heterogeneity is not straightforward so the interpretation of similar values of dispersion is unclear. </p><p id="para33">There are many reasons why the value ofnullmay differ between the United States and Canada. One consideration is a potential difference in the timing of the introduction of two&hyphen;dose vaccination. The Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices and the American Academy of Pediatrics recommended two&hyphen;dose coverage in 1989 &nbsp; <citref rids="ref63">63</citref>. Although the coverage in 2004  appeared similar between the United States and Canada&nbsp; <citref rids="ref38">38</citref>, it is unclear whether this level of coverage was achieved at the same time in both countries. To assess whether a difference in vaccine coverage explains the difference in observednullhere, it would be helpful to run a similar analysis on more recent data. Other factors that could contribute to the difference innullinclude a greater tendency in the United States to conduct contact tracing for susceptible cases and vaccinate close contacts, a greater sensitivity in Canada for reporting milder cases of measles, or greater difficulty of detecting isolated cases via passive surveillance in Canada&nbsp; <citref rids="ref37 ref38">37,38</citref>. More detailed information of the impact of contact investigation, stratification of cases based on disease severity, and quantitative comparison of case ascertainment in passive versus active surveillance would provide additional insight. </p></section>
<section level="2" id="section15"><title>Smallpox transmission</title><p id="para34"> Smallpox control is already known to have been very effective&semi;however, our analysis of smallpox transmission in Europe around the time of eradication quantifies the impact of interventions for control&lpar;Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig4">Figure&#146;4</figref>nullshowing that there was a reduction ofnullfor secondary cases by 75 &percnt;compared to primary cases. This effect of control may be an underestimate because it does not account for the possibility of late arrival of imported cases during the course of infection. Since the infectious period of imported primary cases may have occurred outside of the country of residence, the actualnullfor primary cases might be higher than seen in the data and thus the effect of control may be even greater than our estimates indicate. </p><p id="para35">Here we have shown hownullfor each generation can be quantitatively compared, using published transmission data. Our analysis of differences in the transmissibility of cases as an outbreak develops is not unique&lpar;see for example&nbsp; <citref rids="ref64">64</citref>null. However, previously published methods rely on symptom&hyphen;onset data to determinenullat various stages of an outbreak and thus these approaches could not be performed on the smallpox data set. </p><p id="para36">Aside from the change innull, the marked increase in degree of transmission heterogeneity for secondary cases&lpar;as evidenced by a decreased in the observed value of<equ id="equ58" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
nullsuggests that control tended to be individual&hyphen;specific rather than population&hyphen;wide. Here, individual&hyphen;specific control refers to an intervention that is completely effective for 75 &percnt;of cases but not effective at all for the remaining cases, whereas population&hyphen;wide control refers to an intervention that reduces the transmissibility of each case by 75 &percnt;&nbsp; <citref rids="ref23">23</citref>. For individual&hyphen;specific control, a large number of cases become dead ends for infection so the observed degree of heterogeneity increases&nbsp; <citref rids="ref19 ref20">19,20</citref>. In contrast, the observed degree of transmission&lpar;as quantified by the dispersion parameternullwould not change for population&hyphen;wide intervention. The support for individual&hyphen;specific control is highly consistent with the quarantine and ring vaccination methods employed during smallpox elimination efforts&nbsp; <citref rids="ref12">12</citref>. These observations show how understanding the variation in both the strength and heterogeneity of transmission can provide insight into disease dynamics. </p></section>
<section level="2" id="section16"><title>Monkeypox transmission</title><p id="para37"> Our analysis of monkeypox in the Democratic Republic of Congo demonstrates how our method can be used to inform surveillance planning. In particular, by determining the number of chains that needed to be observed in order to detect various degrees of change innull, we provide perspective regarding the extent to which the 760  monkeypox cases observed between 2005  and 2007 &nbsp; <citref rids="ref56">56</citref>can provide enough information to detect increased transmissibility&lpar;Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig7">Figure&#146;7</figref>null. Based on our power analysis, it appears that a change innulldue to declining population immunity should be detectable, sincenullis expected to approach<equ id="equ59" type="inline">
<tex>
$R_0=0.8$

</tex></equ>
&nbsp; <citref rids="ref43">43</citref>. However, this result needs to be interpreted in context because our model assumes that the probability of case observation is high and that distinct infection clusters can be determined. Given the logistical challenges of recent surveillance efforts&nbsp; <citref rids="ref56">56</citref>, these assumptions are unlikely to have been met, so the realized power for detecting a change innullis probably lower. Nevertheless, this simulation analysis provides perspective concerning the trade&hyphen;offs of thoroughness in detecting and characterizing cases versus observing cases within a greater catchment area for any future surveillance efforts for which measurement ofnullis of interest. </p><p id="para38">When we focused on more detailed generation&hyphen;level data for monkeypox transmission from 1980 &ndash;1984 , we found no support for enhancement ofnullby highly&hyphen;connected individuals in secondary generations&lpar;Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig5">Figure&#146;5</figref>null. This suggests that the high degree of transmission heterogeneity may be caused by biological factors, rather than variability in social contact. However, a key assumption of the network model we tested is that primary cases are infected at random relative to their degree&lpar;as might reasonably be expected for a zoonotic infectionnull. It may be that high&hyphen;connected individuals are also more likely to get a primary infection. If this were the case, then highly connected individuals would contribute to heterogeneity of both primary and secondary transmission. Meanwhile, the lack of increasednullfor secondary transmission provides assurance that significant viral adaptation is not occurring, although local depletion of susceptible individuals within small sub&hyphen;networks such as households could obscure signals of viral adaptation. </p><p id="para39">We found that humans and animals in contact with humans produce similar numbers of human cases&lpar;Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig6">Figure&#146;6</figref>null. Moreover, we estimated that 25 &percnt;of human exposure to an infected animal lead to at least one detected human case. While the truncated negative binomial distribution produces unbiased estimates of transmission parameters, the confidence intervals can be quite large&nbsp; <citref rids="ref19">19</citref>. Furthermore, the {\emapriori}<emph type="italic">a priori</emph>specification that the offspring distribution will be characterized by negative binomial distribution is a strong assumption. Thus the inferred proportion of animal&hyphen;to&hyphen;human exposures leading to infection deserves cautious interpretation. Nevertheless, this type of analysis could be useful for informing surveillance and detection efforts in wildlife species. In particular, since the overall incidence of monkeypox is quite low&lpar;14.42 per 10 , 000  per year&nbsp; <citref rids="ref56">56</citref>null, the observation that there may be only 4 &hyphen;fold more infected animals in contact with humans than the number of observed infection clusters provides perspective on the fact that monkeypox virus has only been isolated from one wild animal&lpar;as of 2011 null&nbsp; <citref rids="ref58">58</citref>. If contacts with infected animals account for a small proportion of overall human contact with reservoir species, the use of targeted&hyphen;surveillance strategies that can exploit spatial&hyphen;temporal data to identify likely hotspots of incidence&nbsp; <citref rids="ref58 ref59 ref65">58,59,65</citref>may be essential to improve detection efforts in wildlife hosts. </p></section>
<section level="2" id="section17"><title>Sensitivity to a small number of large transmission events</title><p id="para40"> As with any model selection or measurement scheme, a small portion of the data, or even a single data point, can have a particularly large influence. For example, the largest transmission chain in the Canadian measles data consists of 155  cases while the second largest chain has just 30  cases. Moreover, the chain with 155  cases was associated with a religious community that resisted immunization, thus it could be argued that this chain is not representative of the population as a whole. If the 155 &hyphen;case chain were excluded from thenullanalysis, our method would no longer find statistical support for a difference innullbetween the United States and Canada&lpar;S material, Text S1null. </p><p id="para41">However, rather than excluding a possible outlier, our preference is to treat the data at face value. From a modeling perspective, it is often unclear whether the mechanism responsible for a purported outlier is absent in the rest of the data. For example, in the case of Canadian measles data set, the second largest chain of 30  cases was also associated with a religious community. In addition, a particularly large chain does not represent a single large transmission event, but rather an entire group of individuals who collectively had relatively high transmission. Mathematically, a high degree of transmission heterogeneity&lpar;represented by low values of<equ id="equ60" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
nullis expected to have a big tail for the distribution of the number of cases that each case causes&nbsp; <citref rids="ref23">23</citref>&semi;thus, a large transmission event or chain in a set of data will increase the estimated value ofnull, but will also decrease the estimated value of<equ id="equ61" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
. A lower<equ id="equ62" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
will be associated with a wider confidence interval fornulland this would make it harder for our analysis to find a statistically significant difference innull&nbsp; <citref rids="ref19 ref20">19,20</citref>. Thus our modeling framework has a built&hyphen;in mechanism that compensates for large transmission events and chains that are consequences of intrinsic population&hyphen;level or individual&hyphen;level mechanisms of heterogeneity. </p></section>
<section level="2" id="section18"><title>Impact of imperfect case observation</title><p id="para42"> A key caveat of our analyses is that we have assumed perfect observation of cases. Some surveillance programs, such as measles in the United States, have documented evidence of high case observation&nbsp; <citref rids="ref36">36</citref>. However, this level of case ascertainment cannot be expected of all diseases, particularly those such as MERS&hyphen;CoV that are quite new. Meanwhile, even meticulously collected data are prone to multiple sources of observation bias due to limited surveillance resources, subclinical infections, laboratory error, or other factors. </p><p id="para43">When the limitations of observation can be quantified, likelihood calculation for observed transmission events can be adjusted appropriately&nbsp; <citref rids="ref19 ref20">19,20</citref>. The challenge is that the limitations of surveillance systems and case ascertainment are often difficult to quantify. An alternative to explicit correction of observation bias is to simply consider what level of observation bias would impact key results. For example, in our analysis of the difference between animal&hyphen;to&hyphen;human and human&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmission of monkeypox, it is quite possible that a number of animal&hyphen;to&hyphen;human infections are unobserved&horbar;particularly if the resulting primary infection is mild and has no further transmission. When we treated observation of an infection cluster as an all&hyphen;or&hyphen;none process with an independent probability, <equ id="equ63" type="inline">
<tex>
$p_o$

</tex></equ>
, that each case would activate surveillance&lpar;thus implying many isolated cases would be unobservednull, our preferred model of transmission remained stable even for a<equ id="equ64" type="inline">
<tex>
$p_o$

</tex></equ>
of 0.1&lpar;S material, Text S1null. This provides re&hyphen;assurance that our methodology is not necessarily sensitive to imperfect observation. However, different data sets or a different type of observation bias could yield less stable results. </p></section>
<section level="2" id="section19"><title>Other modeling extensions</title><p id="para44"> In our analyses, we have allowed for at most two values ofnulland<equ id="equ65" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
in a data set rather than permitting additional stratification or a continuous distribution of values. These simplifications are not always valid assumptions. However, modifications to the likelihood calculation can often be made in order to accommodate more complicated data sets so that our framework for detecting a difference innullcan be utilized. For example, the offspring generating function used for the likelihood calculation can be written in terms of a continuous variable that provides a smooth transition between the extreme limits of classification. In fact this approach has been used to investigate whether there is a temporal trend of measles transmissibility in the United States&nbsp; <citref rids="ref61">61</citref>. </p><p id="para45">Although we have mainly focused on differences innullbetween two populations, our method can also be used to identify whether these populations differ in the observed degree of heterogeneity. Clustering of individuals with higher transmissibility may favor models with two distinct values for<equ id="equ66" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
whenever two distinct values ofnullare observed. Meanwhile, situations that would favor a model with two distinct values of<equ id="equ67" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
and one value ofnullcould arise if different mechanisms of control were used to maintainnullbelow a given threshold, as seen in the smallpox example. Regardless of which model is the preferred model for a given data set, the estimated or assigned value of<equ id="equ68" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
can be useful to assess the overall degree of transmission heterogeneity and the likely presence of super&hyphen;spreaders&nbsp; <citref rids="ref20 ref23">20,23</citref>. On the other hand, the specific mechanism of heterogeneity&lpar;e. g. differencesin transmission potential among cases versus clustering of susceptible individualsnullcannot be ascertained from estimation of<equ id="equ69" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
alone. </p></section>
<section level="2" id="section20"><title>Limitations</title><p id="para46"> Our analysis is focused on determining whether there is statistical support for a difference innullfor individuals having a specific trait. Also, as exemplified by our direct comparison to the random network model&lpar;Figure&nbsp;<figref rids="fig5">Figure&#146;5</figref>and Table&nbsp;<tblref rids="tbl4">Table&#146;4</tblref>null, we can evaluate specific models of transmission. However, in the absence of a mechanistically derived model, our analysis cannot identify the cause of differences innull. For&hyphen;example, population&hyphen;level factors favoring transmission&lpar;e. g. increasedhuman densitynullcannot be directly distinguished from biological factors&lpar;e. g. evolutionaryadaptationnull. Furthermore, the decrease in secondary transmission due to local depletion of susceptibles cannot be directly distinguished from decreases due to control mechanisms. Instead, our method needs to be considered as a tool that can identify differences in transmission&lpar;e. g. temporaltrends for MERS&hyphen;CoV, and geographic distinctions in measlesnullor quantify changes in transmission that are expected to occur&lpar;e. g. decreasedtransmission due to quarantine of smallpox cases or ring vaccinationnull. </p></section></section>
<section level="1" id="section21"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="para47"> By addressing diverse questions within varied data sets, we have demonstrated that a set of inter&hyphen;related models within a branching process framework allows rigorous statistical assessment of whether particular characteristics of infectious cases impact transmission potential. We have focused on subcritical diseases, in large part because the type of surveillance data gathered for these diseases is most compatible with our computational approach. For MERS&hyphen;CoV, we evaluated the possibility of a temporal trend towards decreasingnullthat may indicate stronger control, but did not find enough statistical evidence to confirm this finding. For measles, we found evidence of geographic variability that provides potential insight into the effectiveness of surveillance and public health interventions. For smallpox, we identified signatures of effective control by comparing primary and secondary transmission. For monkeypox, we found that the most parsimonious models are ones that incorporate a high degree of transmission heterogeneity, but do not differentiate between animal&hyphen;to&hyphen;human transmission, transmission of primary cases, and transmission of secondary cases. In general, the statistical support we observed for models that allow flexible inference of bothnulland<equ id="equ70" type="inline">
<tex>
$k$

</tex></equ>
reinforces the importance of quantifying both the strength and variability of disease transmissibility. By providing a diverse array of applications and analyses, the method we have demonstrated can increase the value of existing surveillance data and improve strategies for future data collection. Through identifying specific risk factors for transmissibility and by assessing different sources of transmission heterogeneity, we hope that disease monitoring and control interventions can become more targeted and thus more effective. </p><p id="para48">addcontentslinetocsectionReferences</p></section></body><back><refs><title>References</title>
<cit id="ref1" num="1" type="journal"><author><surname>{DeSerres}</surname><initial>G</initial></author><author><surname>Gay</surname><initial>NJ</initial></author><author><surname>Farrington</surname><initial>CP</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2000 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl>Epidemiology of transmissiblediseases after elimination</cit-tl><pub-tl>The American Journal of Epidemiology</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>1039</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1048</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref2" num="2" type="journal"><author><surname>Farrington</surname><initial>CP</initial></author><author><surname>Kanaan</surname><initial>MN</initial></author><author><surname>Gay</surname><initial>NJ</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2003 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl>Branching process models for surveillance of infectious diseases controlled by mass vaccination</cit-tl><pub-tl>Biostatistics</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>279</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>95</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref3" num="3" type="journal"><author><surname>Jansen</surname><initial>Vaa</initial></author><author><surname>Stollenwerk</surname><initial>N</initial></author><author><surname>Jensen</surname><initial>HJ</initial></author><author><surname>Ramsay</surname><initial>ME</initial></author><author><surname>Edmunds</surname><initial>WJ</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2003 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Measles outbreaks in a population with declining vaccine uptake</cit-tl><pub-tl>Science</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage> 804 </fpage></pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref4" num="4" type="journal"><author><surname>Woolhouse</surname><initial>M</initial></author><author><surname>Gowtage</surname><initial>-</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2005 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Host range and emerging andreemerging pathogens</cit-tl><pub-tl>Emerging Infectious Diseases</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>1842</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1847</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref5" num="5" type="journal"><author><surname>Jones</surname><initial>KE</initial></author><author><surname>Patel</surname><initial>NG</initial></author><author><surname>Levy</surname><initial>MA</initial></author><author><surname>Storeygard</surname><initial>A</initial></author><author><surname>Balk</surname><initial>D</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2008 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl>Global trends in emerging infectious diseases</cit-tl><pub-tl>Nature</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>990</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref6" num="6" type="journal"><author><surname>Lloyd</surname><initial>-</initial></author><author><surname>George</surname><initial>D</initial></author><author><surname>Pepin</surname><initial>KM</initial></author><author><surname>Pitzer</surname><initial>VE</initial></author><author><surname>Pulliam</surname><initial>JRC</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2009 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Epidemic dynamics at the human&hyphen; animal interface</cit-tl><pub-tl>Science</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>1362</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>7</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref7" num="7" type="journal"><author><surname>Omer</surname><initial>SB</initial></author><author><surname>Salmon</surname><initial>DA</initial></author><author><surname>Orenstein</surname><initial>WA</initial></author><author><surname>deHart</surname><initial>MP</initial></author><author><surname>Halsey</surname><initial>N</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2009 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Vaccine refusal,  mandatory immunization,  and the risks of vaccine&hyphen; preventable diseases</cit-tl><pub-tl>New England Journal of Medicine</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>1981</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1988</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref8" num="8" type="journal"><author><surname>Antia</surname><initial>R</initial></author><author><surname>Regoes</surname><initial>RR</initial></author><author><surname>Koella</surname><initial>JC</initial></author><author><surname>Bergstrom</surname><initial>CT</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2003 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> The role of evolution inthe emergence of infectious diseases</cit-tl><pub-tl>Nature</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>8</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>11</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref9" num="9" type="journal"><author><surname>Arinaminpathy</surname><initial>N</initial></author><author><surname>McLean</surname><initial>AR</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2009 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl>Evolution and emergence of novel human infections</cit-tl><pub-tl>Proceedings of the Royal Society B Biological Sciences</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>3937</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>43</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref10" num="10" type="journal"><author><surname>Pepin</surname><initial>KM</initial></author><author><surname>Lass</surname><initial>S</initial></author><author><surname>Pulliam</surname><initial>JRC</initial></author><author><surname>Read</surname><initial>AF</initial></author><author><surname>Lloyd</surname><initial>-</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2010 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Identifying genetic markers of adaptation for surveillance of viral host jumps</cit-tl><pub-tl>Nature Reviews Microbiology</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>802</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>13</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref11" num="11" type="journal"><author><surname>Funk</surname><initial>S</initial></author><author><surname>Salath</surname><initial>M</initial></author><author><surname>Jansen</surname><initial>VAA</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2010 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Modelling the influence of human behaviour on the spread of infectious diseases&colon; a review</cit-tl><pub-tl>Journal of The Royal Society Interface</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>1247</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1256</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref12" num="12" type="journal"><author><surname>Fenner</surname><initial>F</initial></author><author><surname>Henderson</surname><initial>DA</initial></author><author><surname>Arita</surname><initial>I</initial></author><author><surname>Jezek</surname><initial>Z</initial></author><author><surname>Ladnyi</surname><initial>ID</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>1988 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Smallpox and its Eradication</cit-tl><pub-tl>Geneva World Health Organization,   pp. </pub-tl></cit>
<cit id="ref13" num="13" type="journal"><author><surname>Reilly</surname><initial>KM</initial></author><author><surname>Durry</surname><initial>E</initial></author><author><surname>ul</surname><initial>~</initial></author><author><surname>Quddus</surname><initial>A</initial></author><author><surname>Abid</surname><initial>N</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2012 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> The effect of mass immunisation campaigns and new oral poliovirus vaccines on the incidence of poliomyelitis in pakistan and afghanistan,  2001 &hyphen; 11 &colon; a retrospective analysis</cit-tl><pub-tl>The Lancet</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>491</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>498</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref14" num="14" type="journal"><author><surname>Minor</surname><initial>PD</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2012 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Polio vaccines and the eradication of poliomyelitis</cit-tl><pub-tl>The Lancet</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>454</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>455</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref15" num="15" type="journal"><author><surname>Matthews</surname><initial>L</initial></author><author><surname>Woolhouse</surname><initial>M</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2005 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> New approaches to quantifying the spread of infection</cit-tl><pub-tl>Nature reviews Microbiology</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>529</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>36</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref16" num="16" type="journal"><author><surname>Grassly</surname><initial>NC</initial></author><author><surname>Fraser</surname><initial>C</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2008 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Mathematical models of infectious disease transmission</cit-tl><pub-tl>Nature reviews Microbiology</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>477</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>87</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref17" num="17" type="journal"><author><surname>Lipsitch</surname><initial>M</initial></author><author><surname>Cohen</surname><initial>T</initial></author><author><surname>Cooper</surname><initial>B</initial></author><author><surname>Robins</surname><initial>JM</initial></author><author><surname>Ma</surname><initial>S</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2003 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Transmission dynamics and control of severe acute respiratory syndrome</cit-tl><pub-tl>Science</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>1966</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1970</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref18" num="18" type="journal"><author><surname>Harbarth</surname><initial>S</initial></author><author><surname>Samore</surname><initial>MH</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2005 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Antimicrobial resistance determinants and future control</cit-tl><pub-tl>Emerging infectious diseases</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>794</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>801</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref19" num="19" type="journal"><author><surname>Blumberg</surname><initial>S</initial></author><author><surname>Lloyd</surname><initial>-</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2013 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Comparing methods for estimating<equ id="equ71" type="inline">
<tex>
$R_0$

</tex></equ>
fromthe size distribution of subcritical transmission chains</cit-tl><pub-tl>Epidemics</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>131</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>145</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref20" num="20" type="journal"><author><surname>Blumberg</surname><initial>S</initial></author><author><surname>Lloyd</surname><initial>-</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2013 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl>Inference of<equ id="equ72" type="inline">
<tex>
$R_0$

</tex></equ>
and TransmissionHeterogeneity from the Size Distribution of Stuttering Chains</cit-tl><pub-tl>PLoS Computational Biology</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>e1002993</fpage></pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref21" num="21" type="journal"><author><surname>Diekmann</surname><initial>O</initial></author><author><surname>Heesterbeek</surname><initial>H</initial></author><author><surname>Britton</surname><initial>T</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2012 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Mathematical Tools for Understanding Infectious Disease Dynamics</cit-tl><pub-tl>Princeton,  New Jersey Princeton University Press,   pp. </pub-tl></cit>
<cit id="ref22" num="22" type="journal"><author><surname>Nishiura</surname><initial>H</initial></author><author><surname>Yan</surname><initial>P</initial></author><author><surname>Sleeman</surname><initial>CK</initial></author><author><surname>Mode</surname><initial>CJ</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2012 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Estimating the transmissionpotential of supercritical processes based on the final size distribution ofminor outbreaks</cit-tl><pub-tl>Journal of Theoretical Biology</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>48</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>55</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref23" num="23" type="journal"><author><surname>Lloyd</surname><initial>-</initial></author><author><surname>Schreiber</surname><initial>SJ</initial></author><author><surname>Kopp</surname><initial>PE</initial></author><author><surname>Getz</surname><initial>WM</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2005 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl>Superspreading and the effect of individual variation on disease emergence</cit-tl><pub-tl>Nature</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>355</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>9</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref24" num="24" type="journal"><author><surname>van</surname><initial>Boven</initial></author><author><surname>Koopmans</surname><initial>M</initial></author><author><surname>Du</surname><initial>~</initial></author><author><surname>Meijer</surname><initial>A</initial></author><author><surname>Klinkenberg</surname><initial>D</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2007 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Detecting emerging transmissibility of avian influenza virus in human households</cit-tl><pub-tl>PLoS Comput Biol</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage> e145</fpage></pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref25" num="25" type="journal"><author><surname>Alexander</surname><initial>HK</initial></author><author><surname>Day</surname><initial>T</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2010 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Risk factors for the evolutionary emergence of pathogens</cit-tl><pub-tl>Journal of the Royal Society,  Interface</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>1455</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1474</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref26" num="26" type="journal"><author><surname>Harris</surname><initial>TE</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2002 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> The Theory of Branching Processes</cit-tl><pub-tl>Toronto Dover,   pp. </pub-tl></cit>
<cit id="ref27" num="27" type="journal"><author><surname>Wilf</surname><initial>HS</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>1990 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> generatingfunctionology</cit-tl><pub-tl>Academic Press,  London. </pub-tl></cit>
<cit id="ref28" num="28" type="journal"><author><surname>Lange</surname><initial>K</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2010 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Applied Probability</cit-tl><pub-tl>New York Springer,  second edition,   pp. </pub-tl></cit>
<cit id="ref29" num="29" type="journal"><author><surname>Anderson</surname><initial>RM</initial></author><author><surname>May</surname><initial>RM</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>1991 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Infectious Diseases of Humans&colon; Dynamics and Control</cit-tl><pub-tl>New York Oxford University Press,   pp. </pub-tl></cit>
<cit id="ref30" num="30" type="journal"><author><surname>Bolker</surname><initial>BM</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2008 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Ecological Models and Data in R</cit-tl><pub-tl>Princeton,  New Jersey Princeton University Press,   pp. </pub-tl></cit>
<cit id="ref31" num="31" type="journal"><author><surname>Akaike</surname><initial>HAI</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>1974 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> A New Look at the Statistical Model Identification</cit-tl><pub-tl>IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>716</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>723</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref32" num="32" type="journal"><author><surname>{WorldHealthOrganization}</surname></author>&lpar;<date><year>2014 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl>Update 15 &colon; summary and literature update as of 9  May 2014 </cit-tl><pub-tl>. </pub-tl></cit>
<cit id="ref33" num="33" type="journal"><author><surname>Breban</surname><initial>R</initial></author><author><surname>Riou</surname><initial>J</initial></author><author><surname>Fontanet</surname><initial>A</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2013 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Interhuman transmissibility of middle east respiratory syndrome coronavirus&colon; estimation of pandemic risk</cit-tl><pub-tl>The Lancet</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>694</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>699</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref34" num="34" type="journal"><author><surname>Cauchemez</surname><initial>S</initial></author><author><surname>Fraser</surname><initial>C</initial></author><author><surname>Van</surname><initial>~</initial></author><author><surname>Donnelly</surname><initial>CA</initial></author><author><surname>Riley</surname><initial>S</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2014 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Middle east respiratory syndrome coronavirus&colon; quantification of the extent of the epidemic,  surveillance biases,  and transmissibility</cit-tl><pub-tl>The Lancet infectious diseases</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>50</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>56</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref35" num="35" type="journal"><author><surname>Ferguson</surname><initial>NM</initial></author><author><surname>Van</surname><initial>~</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2014 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Identification of mers&hyphen; cov in dromedary camels</cit-tl><pub-tl>The Lancet infectious diseases</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>93</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>94</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref36" num="36" type="journal"><author><surname>Harpaz</surname><initial>R</initial></author><author><surname>Papania</surname><initial>MJ</initial></author><author><surname>McCauley</surname><initial>MM</initial></author><author><surname>Redd</surname><initial>SB</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2004 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Has surveillance been adequate to detect endemic measles in the United States?</cit-tl><pub-tl>The Journal of infectious diseases  Suppl S191&ndash; . </pub-tl></cit>
<cit id="ref37" num="37" type="journal"><author><surname>Guris</surname><initial>D</initial></author><author><surname>Harpaz</surname><initial>R</initial></author><author><surname>Redd</surname><initial>SB</initial></author><author><surname>Smith</surname><initial>NJ</initial></author><author><surname>Papania</surname><initial>MJ</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2004 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Measles surveillance in the United States&colon; an overview</cit-tl><pub-tl>The Journal of infectious diseases</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>S177</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>84</lpage> </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref38" num="38" type="journal"><author><surname>{DeSerres}</surname><initial>G</initial></author><author><surname>Markowski</surname><initial>F</initial></author><author><surname>Toth</surname><initial>E</initial></author><author><surname>Landry</surname><initial>M</initial></author><author><surname>Auger</surname><initial>D</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2013 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl>Largest measles epidemic in North America in a decade&ndash; Quebec,  Canada,  2011 &colon; contribution of susceptibility,  serendipity,  and superspreading events</cit-tl><pub-tl>The Journal of infectious diseases</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>990</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>8</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref39" num="39" type="journal"><author><surname>Gay</surname><initial>NJ</initial></author><author><surname>{DeSerres}</surname><initial>G</initial></author><author><surname>Farrington</surname><initial>CP</initial></author><author><surname>Redd</surname><initial>SB</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2004 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl>Assessment of thestatus of measles elimination from reported outbreaks&colon;United States, 1997&ndash;1999  </cit-tl><pub-tl>The Journal of Infectious Diseases  Suppl S36&hyphen; S42. </pub-tl></cit>
<cit id="ref40" num="40" type="journal"><author><surname>King</surname><initial>A</initial></author><author><surname>Varughese</surname><initial>P</initial></author><author><surname>{DeSerres}</surname><initial>G</initial></author><author><surname>Tipples</surname><initial>GA</initial></author><author><surname>Waters</surname><initial>J</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2004 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl>Measles elimination in Canada</cit-tl><pub-tl>The Journal of Infectious Diseases  Suppl S236&ndash; . </pub-tl></cit>
<cit id="ref41" num="41" type="journal"><author><surname>{CentersforDiseaseControlandPrevention}</surname></author>&lpar;<date><year>2012 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl></cit-tl><pub-tl>Documentation and verification of measles,  rubella,  and congenital rubella syndrome elimination in the region of the Americas. </pub-tl></cit>
<cit id="ref42" num="42" type="journal"><author><surname>Jezek</surname><initial>Z</initial></author><author><surname>Fenner</surname><initial>F</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>1988 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl>Human Monkeypox</cit-tl><pub-tl>Basel Karger,   pp. </pub-tl></cit>
<cit id="ref43" num="43" type="journal"><author><surname>Fine</surname><initial>PE</initial></author><author><surname>Jezek</surname><initial>Z</initial></author><author><surname>Grab</surname><initial>B</initial></author><author><surname>Dixon</surname><initial>H</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>1988 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> The transmission potential of monkeypox virus in human populations</cit-tl><pub-tl>International Journal of Epidemiology</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>643</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>50</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref44" num="44" type="journal"><author><surname>Rohani</surname><initial>P</initial></author><author><surname>Zhong</surname><initial>X</initial></author><author><surname>King</surname><initial>Aa</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2010 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Contact network structure explains the changing epidemiology of pertussis</cit-tl><pub-tl>Science&lpar; New York,  NYnull</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>982</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>5</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref45" num="45" type="journal"><author><surname>Cauchemez</surname><initial>S</initial></author><author><surname>Bhattarai</surname><initial>A</initial></author><author><surname>Marchbanks</surname><initial>TL</initial></author><author><surname>Fagan</surname><initial>RP</initial></author><author><surname>Ostroff</surname><initial>S</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2011 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Role of social networks in shaping disease transmission during a community outbreak of 2009  H1N1 pandemic influenza</cit-tl><pub-tl>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>2825</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>30</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref46" num="46" type="journal"><author><surname>Danon</surname><initial>L</initial></author><author><surname>Ford</surname><initial>AP</initial></author><author><surname>House</surname><initial>T</initial></author><author><surname>Jewell</surname><initial>CP</initial></author><author><surname>Keeling</surname><initial>MJ</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2011 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Networks and the epidemiology of infectious disease</cit-tl><pub-tl>Interdisciplinary perspectives on infectious diseases</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage> 284909 </fpage></pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref47" num="47" type="journal"><author><surname>Volz</surname><initial>EM</initial></author><author><surname>Miller</surname><initial>JC</initial></author><author><surname>Galvani</surname><initial>A</initial></author><author><surname>{AncelMeyers}</surname><initial>L</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2011 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl>Effects of heterogeneous and clustered contact patterns on infectious disease dynamics</cit-tl><pub-tl>PLoS computational biology</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage> e1002042</fpage></pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref48" num="48" type="journal"><author><surname>Cauchemez</surname><initial>S</initial></author><author><surname>Ferguson</surname><initial>NM</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2012 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Methods to infer transmission risk factors in complex outbreak data</cit-tl><pub-tl>Journal of the Royal Society,  Interface&sol; the Royal Society</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>456</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>69</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref49" num="49" type="journal"><author><surname>Jezek</surname><initial>Z</initial></author><author><surname>Grab</surname><initial>B</initial></author><author><surname>Dixon</surname><initial>H</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>1987 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Stochastic model for interhuman spread of monkeypox</cit-tl><pub-tl>American Journal of Epidemiology</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>1082</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>92</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref50" num="50" type="journal"><author><surname>Woolhouse</surname><initial>MEJ</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2002 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Population biology of emerging and re&hyphen; emerging pathogens</cit-tl><pub-tl>Trends in microbiology</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>S3</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>7</lpage> </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref51" num="51" type="journal"><author><surname>Yang</surname><initial>Y</initial></author><author><surname>Halloran</surname><initial>ME</initial></author><author><surname>Sugimoto</surname><initial>JD</initial></author><author><surname>Longini</surname><initial>IM</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2007 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Detecting human&hyphen; to&hyphen; human transmission of avian influenza A&lpar; H5N1null</cit-tl><pub-tl>Emerging infectious diseases</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>1348</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>53</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref52" num="52" type="journal"><author><surname>Streicker</surname><initial>DG</initial></author><author><surname>Turmelle</surname><initial>AS</initial></author><author><surname>Vonhof</surname><initial>MJ</initial></author><author><surname>Kuzmin</surname><initial>IV</initial></author><author><surname>McCracken</surname><initial>GF</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2010 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Host phylogeny constrains cross&hyphen; species emergence and establishment of rabies virus in bats</cit-tl><pub-tl>Science</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>676</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>679</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref53" num="53" type="journal"><author><surname>Roy</surname><initial>S</initial></author><author><surname>McElwain</surname><initial>TF</initial></author><author><surname>Wan</surname><initial>Y</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2011 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> A network control theory approach to modeling and optimal control of zoonoses&colon; case study of brucellosis transmission in sub&hyphen; Saharan Africa</cit-tl><pub-tl>PLoS neglected tropical diseases</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage> e1259</fpage></pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref54" num="54" type="journal"><author><surname>Aditama</surname><initial>TY</initial></author><author><surname>Samaan</surname><initial>G</initial></author><author><surname>Kusriastuti</surname><initial>R</initial></author><author><surname>Sampurno</surname><initial>OD</initial></author><author><surname>Purba</surname><initial>W</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2012 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Avian influenza h5n1 transmission in households,  indonesia</cit-tl><pub-tl>PloS one</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage> e29971</fpage></pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref55" num="55" type="journal"><author><surname>Funk</surname><initial>S</initial></author><author><surname>Nishiura</surname><initial>H</initial></author><author><surname>Heesterbeek</surname><initial>H</initial></author><author><surname>Edmunds</surname><initial>WJ</initial></author><author><surname>Checchi</surname><initial>F</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2013 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Identifying transmission cycles at the human&hyphen; animal interface&colon; the role of animal reservoirs in maintaining gambiense human african trypanosomiasis</cit-tl><pub-tl>PLoS computational biology</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage> e1002855</fpage></pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref56" num="56" type="journal"><author><surname>Rimoin</surname><initial>AW</initial></author><author><surname>Mulembakani</surname><initial>PM</initial></author><author><surname>Johnston</surname><initial>SC</initial></author><author><surname>Smith</surname><initial>JOL</initial></author><author><surname>Kisalu</surname><initial>NK</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2010 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Major increase in human monkeypox incidence 30  years after smallpox vaccination campaigns cease in the Democratic Republic of Congo</cit-tl><pub-tl>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>16262</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>16267</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref57" num="57" type="journal"><author><surname>Lloyd</surname><initial>-</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2013 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Vacated niches,  competitive release and the community ecology of pathogen eradication</cit-tl><pub-tl>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B Biological Sciences . </pub-tl></cit>
<cit id="ref58" num="58" type="journal"><author><surname>Fuller</surname><initial>T</initial></author><author><surname>Thomassen</surname><initial>Ha</initial></author><author><surname>Mulembakani</surname><initial>PM</initial></author><author><surname>Johnston</surname><initial>SC</initial></author><author><surname>Lloyd</surname><initial>-</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2011 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Using remote sensing to map the risk of human monkeypox virus in the Congo Basin</cit-tl><pub-tl>EcoHealth</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>14</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>25</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref59" num="59" type="journal"><author><surname>Thomassen</surname><initial>HA</initial></author><author><surname>Fuller</surname><initial>T</initial></author><author><surname>Asefi</surname><initial>-</initial></author><author><surname>Shiplacoff</surname><initial>JAG</initial></author><author><surname>Mulembakani</surname><initial>PM</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2013 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Pathogen&hyphen; host associations and predicted range shifts of human monkeypox in response to climate change in central africa</cit-tl><pub-tl>PLoS ONE</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage> e66071</fpage></pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref60" num="60" type="journal"><author><surname>Assiri</surname><initial>A</initial></author><author><surname>McGeer</surname><initial>A</initial></author><author><surname>Perl</surname><initial>TM</initial></author><author><surname>Price</surname><initial>CS</initial></author><author><surname>Al</surname><initial>~</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2013 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Hospital outbreak of middle east respiratory syndrome coronavirus</cit-tl><pub-tl>New England Journal of Medicine</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>407</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>416</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref61" num="61" type="journal"><author><surname>Blumberg</surname><initial>S</initial></author><author><surname>Enanoria</surname><initial>WTA</initial></author><author><surname>Lloyd</surname><initial>-</initial></author><author><surname>Lietman</surname><initial>TM</initial></author><author><surname>Porco</surname><initial>TC</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2014 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Identifying postelimination trends for the introduction and transmissibility of measles in the united states</cit-tl><pub-tl>American Journal of Epidemiology</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>1375</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1382</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref62" num="62" type="journal"><author><surname>Ferguson</surname><initial>NM</initial></author><author><surname>Fraser</surname><initial>C</initial></author><author><surname>Donnelly</surname><initial>CA</initial></author><author><surname>Ghani</surname><initial>AC</initial></author><author><surname>Anderson</surname><initial>RM</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2004 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Public healthrisk from the avian H5N1 influenza epidemic</cit-tl><pub-tl>Science</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>1</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>5</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref63" num="63" type="journal"><author><surname>{CentersforDiseaseControlandPrevention}</surname></author>&lpar;<date><year>1998 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl>Measles, Mumps, andRubella&ndash;Vaccine Use and Strategies for Elimination of Measles, Rubella, andCongenital Rubella Syndrome and Control of Mumps&colon;Recommendations of theAdvisory Committee on Immunization Practices&lpar;ACIPnull</cit-tl><pub-tl>Morbidity and mortality weekly report</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>1</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>57</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref64" num="64" type="journal"><author><surname>Wallinga</surname><initial>J</initial></author><author><surname>Teunis</surname><initial>P</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2004 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl>Different epidemic curves for severe acute respiratory syndrome reveal similar impacts of control measures</cit-tl><pub-tl>American Journal of Epidemiology</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage>509</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>16</lpage>  </pages>&colon;</cit>
<cit id="ref65" num="65" type="journal"><author><surname>Levine</surname><initial>RS</initial></author><author><surname>Peterson</surname><initial>A</initial></author><author><surname>Yorita</surname><initial>KL</initial></author><author><surname>Carroll</surname><initial>D</initial></author><author><surname>Damon</surname><initial>IK</initial></author>&lpar;<date><year>2007 </year></date>&rpar;<cit-tl> Ecological niche and geographic distribution of human monkeypox in africa</cit-tl><pub-tl>PLoS ONE</pub-tl><vol></vol><pages><fpage> e176</fpage></pages>&colon;</cit>
</refs></back>
<section level="1" id="section22"><title> Supporting information legends</title><p id="para49"><emph type="bold"> Text S1&colon;Methods supplement</emph>Contains 1 nullA detailed description of the likelihood calculations 2 nullSimulation&hyphen;based validation of the method 3 nullSensitivity of measles analyses to a single large chain and 4 nullAn analysis of imperfect observation of monkeypox transmission. </p><p id="para50"><emph type="bold">Text S2&colon;Data supplement</emph>Provides tables and references for all the data used in the analyses. </p></section></article></doc>